Guide to the Correspondence Concerning "The Question of Ezra Pound"
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Esquire correspondence concerning The question of Ezra Pound
1957-1957
YCAL MSS 180
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
The collection consists of alphabetically arranged correspondence between readers of Esquire Magazine and the magazine's editors concerning an article by Richard Rovere on the question of Ezra Pound's possible release from his continuing incarceration in St. Elizabeth's Hospital for the Insane. Respondents include John Dos Passos, Robert Graves, Norman Mailer, Kenneth Rexroth, William Carlos Williams, and Richard Wilbur.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Esquire magazine, 1958.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Esquire Correspondence Concerning "The Question of Ezra Pound" consists of letters received by the magazine in response to an article by Richard Rovere which appeared in the September, 1957 issue. A few letters are accompanied by copies of the magazine's requests for permission to publish. The papers all date from 1957 and have been alphabetically arranged in one series, Correspondence.
Esquire's publisher, Arnold Gingrich, sent out advance copies of Rovere's article to a number of American and English literary figures with a request for comments on "the question of Pound's release" from St. Elizabeth's Hospital in the summer of 1957, then the subject of private discussions between Archibald MacLeish, Robert Frost, and the Department of Justice. Authors who sent comments include Van Wyck Brooks, John Dos Passos, Robert Graves, Norman Mailer, Marianne Moore, Howard Nemerov, Kenneth Rexroth, William Carlos Williams and Richard Wilbur. Many letters contain editorial markings by the Esquire staff. For example, any references by the letter writers to Esquire's solicitation of a response were scored for deletion.
Possibly due to careful selection by the magazine, the literary responders mostly favor Pound's release, often offering to sign petitions or join "any campaign" toward that end. Most, including Marianne Moore, express distaste for Pound's political views but refer to them as "a crotchet" not meriting further punishment. A common theme is that Pound has "suffered enough." Kenneth Rexroth, however, notes that "He is not being punished. If he is sane enough to be guilty of advocating genocide he is being indulged." John Dos Passos warns that "the Kasper disaster has been doing his case a good deal of harm," a reference to the recent Federal arrests of the violent segregationist and Pound disciple John Kasper.
The collection also contains several responses from students and disciples of Pound, including Giovanni Giovannini, T. David Horton, Charles Martell, and Sheri Martinelli. Mostly unsolicited, these letters present lengthy rebuttals of the treason charge; defenses of Pound's economic theories; and passionate denials that Pound is a racist. Martinelli, for example, sends a description of Pound's appreciation for the music of Charlie Parker ("Yardbird").
Finally, there are a few unsolicited responses from Esquire subscribers, most dated late in 1957. These are largely negative and highly critical of both Pound and his supporters. Arpine Hardidiau accuses Pound's sympathizers of being "blindly loyal to one of their select circle. Since when has talent been a justification for viciousness?" Leslie Hedley suggests that "fascist Pound be traded to fascist Franco Spain" along with his "admirers," while J. W. O'Banion writes, "Is he Crazy? Was Hitler, Mussolini, Stalin and Lenin crazy? Hell NO."
Esquire (New York, N.Y.); American literature -- 20th Century; Competency to stand trial -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Treason -- United States; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970; Gingrich, Arnold, 1903-1976; Graves, Robert, 1895-1985; Mailer, Norman, 1923-2007; Martinelli, Sheri; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Political and social views; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Public opinion; Rexroth, Kenneth, 1905-1982; Rovere, Richard H. (Richard Halworth), 1915-1979; Wilbur, Richard, 1921-2017; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; American Civil Liberties Union
- Correspondence, 1957; Series I; 0.21' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1957 Aug (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barolini, Antonio, 1957 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bower, Warren, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1957 Aug (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bryant, William, 1957 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chase, Richard, 1957 Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dos Passos, John, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dreijmanis, J., 1957 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fowlie, Wallace, 1957 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Frank, Joseph, 1957 Aug (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Giovannini, Giovanni, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Graves, Robert, 1957 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hadidiau, Arpine, 1957 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hedley, Leslie, 1957 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Horton, T. David, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lytle, Andrew, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - McCloskey, Burr, 1957 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mailer, Norman, 1957 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Malin, Patrick Murphy
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: American Civil Liberties Union, Box 1, folder 1
  - Martell, Charles, 1957 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Martinelli, Sheri, 1957 Oct (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1957 Aug (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Nemerov, Howard, 1957 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - O'Banion, J. N., 1957 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rodman, Selden, 1957 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Schorer, Mark, 1957 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sitwell, Osbert, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Williamson, Lamar, 1957 Aug (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Wilbur, Richard, 1957 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Unidentified, 1957 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 31)